Security code review of a big codebase
is very difficult. In the beginning,
you are just overwhelmed by the amount
of things you don't understand. However,
there are things you can do to make it
easier and find more bugs by reviewing
the code. In this video, I will show them on
the example of my bug in Golang's HTML parser,
which is in scope of Google
Open Source Bug Bounty. Enjoy!
The first step is understanding, on a high
level, what you are reviewing. I usually do
this by just using the product and by reading the
documentation. But by no means this one stepis
enough to make a complex codebase easy to review.
Especially, when we are talking about HTML parser,
because HTML is extremely complex with hundreds of
states, namespaces, different parsing rules… But
the fact that the whole library is complex doesn't
mean that every single line does crazy things. The
whole library is composed of many small pieces
which by themselves are easy to understand.
The first thing that I do when I'm
jumping to reviewing a code like
this is I find a small piece like this,
a piece that fits onto a single screen,
and I try to understand what happens there.
This gives my brain the signal that it's not
as overwhelming as I initially thought. And this
does not have to lead me to a bug straight away.
Let's be honest, when I'm approaching a target
like this, I am not hoping to find an easy bounty
in one day. Especially since I am not an HTML
expert or an XSS god. The code I stumbled upon is
this function that's used to parse HTML comments.
This is how HTML comments normally look like.
And you may be wondering: what's the point of
messing up with comments? what
could I potentially achieve?
So imagine I have a website where I allow users
to use simple HTML in their descriptions. For
simplicity, let's only allow header tags. So I
write some code that takes the description
from the user, parses the HTML, and checks whether
all tags that are in this HTML are allowed or not.
If they are not, I forbid the user from saving
this description. If they are, I'd consider this
description safe and I show it to other users,
where this HTML is being parsed in their browsers.
So the HTML is parsed twice: once by my code,
which uses Golang's HTML parser, and then by
the browser of my potential victim. If I can
find any inconsistency between these parsers,
I can hide some XSS payloads so that the
validator doesn't see those payloads,
but they are executed in the browsers
in the context of the victim.
When you are looking for bugs in libraries
like this, you have to come up with these
attack scenarios yourself. Just make sure
that you are using the library correctly,
because if you misuse it,
you will not be rewarded.
So let's come back to the comment
syntax. This is the typical comment.
But the specifications of how parsers should
parse the comments mention a few exceptions.
One rule says that if a > character
is immediately after the beginning,
this is considered an empty comment. Another
rule says that if a comment is closed with
this sequence: !-->, it is also considered a valid
comment closing. Golang's library had no problems
with applying these two rules. But tell me,
what do you think should happen with this?
If you combine the logic from these two rules, you
should interpret this as a valid empty comment.
However, there is nothing in the specification
saying that these two can be used together.
It means this is only a comment opening,
and that's also how browsers process this.
But Golang's HTML parser saw this as an
empty comment. So if I use a payload like this,
then my hypothetical validator would see
an empty comment first, and then an H1 tag
with some attributes, which are considered
safe. So this description would be allowed.
But then, it would be shown to users and processed
by their browsers. And the browser would see here
only a comment opening and the H1 tag would
be the comment's content. Then, the comment
would be closed, and the rest will be processed as
valid HTML. This way, we smuggled an a tag past
the validator, and the XSS can execute in the
victim's browser if they click on this link.
Google paid me $3,133.70 for this bug.
If you want to learn more about XSSes,
check out this video with some of my conclusions
after studying 174 bug bounty XSS reports.
For now, thank you for watching, and goodbye!